Guide to the Jack Doroshow / Flawless Sabrina Papers MSS.594
Fales Library and Special Collections
Jack Doroshow / Flawless Sabrina Papers
1937-2018
1967-2010
Fales Library and Special Collections
Doroshow, Jack
Carman, Curtis
MSS.594
37 linear feet in 44 manuscript boxes, 6 small flat boxes, 1 oversize flat box, 3 flat-file folders, 1 folder in a shared oversize flat box, 6 audiocassettes in a shared cassette box, 2 custom flat boxes, and born-digital carriers in a shared CD box.
18 Gigabytes in 54 computer files
6 audiocassettes
Jack Doroshow (1939-2017), also known as the drag queen Flawless Sabrina, was a performer, writer, producer, and mentor to LGBTQ community members. As Sabrina, Doroshow was a well-known drag queen, making appearances in New York City area clubs, and organizing and hosting drag queen pageants during the 1960s. Sabrina built on her success in the entertainment industry after her involvement in the 1968 film The Queen which documented her 1967 Miss All-America Camp Beauty Contest. The Jack Doroshow / Flawless Sabrina Papers consist of materials created and collected by Doroshow related to his career and personal life. The bulk of the materials in this collection document Doroshow's successes and failures in the entertainment industry, including files on the movie The Queen; an unrealized 1980s television show The Apple Pie Show with John Waters and Divine; and also proposals and scripts on a variety of other movie, television, and theatrical projects Doroshow attempted throughout the 1970s to the 2000s. The collection also consists of material on the drag community in New York City during the 1960s through 2010s, with some focusing specifically on Flawless Sabrina's drag career through photographs, event invitations, and show cue cards. Materials on the drag community include invitations, publications, and photographs. This collection has numerous issues of the weekly publication Michael's Thing which connected the gay community with restaurants, gay-friendly businesses, and promotional information on special events, drag shows, and dance clubs in New York City during the 1970s and 1980s. Doroshow's papers also include files on his business ventures including his antique selling, children's quilts, music production, and magazine publication. A large collection of notebooks and notepads document his thoughts, writing ideas, and partial journal entries. Doroshow's personal files include correspondence, photographs, appointment books, and resumes.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Curtis Carman and the Jack A. Doroshow Revocable Trust in December 2019; the accession number associated with this purchase is 2019.078.
Appraisal
Three carriers containing born-digital material were removed from the collection because they were blank or not able to be imaged. 80 commercial recordings with no connection to Jack Doroshow/Flawless Sabrina were removed from the collection. 23 publications had existing copies within the library and were removed from the collection.
Arrangement
This collection is organized into six series. Each is arranged chronologically within. The first series is arranged further into three subseries.
Series I. Film, TV Shows, and Theater
Subseries I.A. The Queen
Subseries I.B. The Apple Pie Show
Subseries I.C. General Project Files
Series II. Drag Events and Ephemera
Series III. Writings
Series IV. Business Projects
Series V. Music Production
Series VI. Personal Files
Biographical Note
Jack Doroshow (1939-2017), also known as the drag queen Flawless Sabrina, was a performer, writer, producer, and mentor to LGBTQ community members. In 1959 Doroshow along with two friends staged a drag pageant in Philadelphia, which eventually led to the creation of his persona Flawless Sabrina, who served as pageant hostess. He eventually formed his own company, Nationals Academy, to tap into the drag show subculture through pageants in large and small American cities. His most famous pageant was the 1967 Miss All-America Camp Beauty Contest of which the footage was made into a 1968 documentary The Queen by Frank Simon. Sabrina acted as mistress of ceremonies and film narrator. The success of the documentary resulted in an increase in speaking engagements and television appearances. Doroshow also sold antiques, as well as produced projects in film, television, and theater. He was well-known as Mother Sabrina, a mentor to not only drag performers, but other members of the LGBTQ community. He passed away in 2017.
Born-Digital Access Policies and Procedures
Advance notice is required for the use of computer records. Original physical digital media is restricted. An access terminal for born-digital materials in the collection is available by appointment for reading room viewing and listening only. Researchers may view an item's original container and/or carrier, but the physical carriers themselves are not available for use because of preservation concerns.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Audiovisual materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact Fales Library and Special Collections, special.collections@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596 with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Scope and Contents
The Jack Doroshow/Flawless Sabrina Papers consist of paper and electronic files created and collected by Jack Doroshow documenting his personal life and career as Flawless Sabrina the drag queen, actor, writer, and producer. This collection provides insight into the work and life of a drag entertainer and business person in New York during the 1960s through 2010s, including his exploration into a variety of business and entertainment ventures, his struggles financially supporting himself as an artist, and his relationships with artists and performers. This collection also documents the evolution of the drag community through the years within New York City.
Doroshow's various projects within the music, television, theatrical, and film industries include the 1968 documentary film The Queen; an unrealized talkshow, The Apple Pie Show, with John Waters and Divine; and the movie More, More, More. Project files in this collection typically include proposal packets, scripts, budgets, and correspondence. Documentation on Jack's career as Flawless Sabrina and also the drag queen community in general is represented through photographs, event promotional material, set plans, notes, and cue cards. Large photograph collages once mounted on Doroshow's apartment walls contain images of Doroshow with friends and partners at home and events throughout his life.
This collection contains a notable amount of issues dating from 1973 to 1984 of Michael's Thing, a guide to information and entertainment for the LGBTQ community within the New York City area. This weekly publication provided articles, interviews, and advertisements which focused on the interests of the community including drag shows, dance clubs, and special events. These issues not only document popular events and places during this time, but Doroshow was also a contributing writer. A large number of loose notes, notepads, and notebooks date from the 1970s to the 2010s, containing Dorowshow's ideas, thoughts, production notes, to do lists, quotes, brief journal entries, and sketches.
While working on his various entertainment industry projects, Doroshow supported himself through successful and unsuccessful business ventures including selling antiques, children's quilts, and two unrealized magazines, Reflections and Casino. His struggles to financially support himself and maintain his rent-controlled apartment in New York are well-documented in this collection, especially as he grew elderly, relying on his community to assist him. Doroshow's role as a mentor to the LGBTQ community is evident in his correspondence and notes with performers and friends, as well as appearances where he would share his experiences with others. This collection also contains material on his personal life, including resumes, and family photographs, as well as material he accumulated on partners and various people in his life.
Drag shows; Female impersonators.; Gay activists.; Gay artists.; Drag mothers; LGBTQ+ activism; Screenplays; Scripts.; Notes (documents); Color prints (photographs); Drag community; Drag queens in motion pictures; Drag queens; Carman, Curtis; Waters, John, 1946-; Divine, 1945-1988
- Series I. Film, TV Shows, and Theater, 1959-2005; 7 Linear Feet in 9 manuscript boxes, 1 flat box, 1 flat-file folder, and 2 shared boxes with items.; 5 audiocassettes; 6 Megabytes in 1 computer file
  Scope and Contents
  This series consists of files related to Doroshow's projects connected to various movie, television, and theater projects, as either Jack Doroshow or Flawless Sabrina.
  Arrangement
  This series is arranged into three subseries and organized chronologically within.
  - Subseries I.A. The Queen, 1959-2002, undated
    This subseries includes files related to the 1968 documentary film The Queen. The film covers the 1967 Miss All-America Camp Beauty Contest in New York City in which Flawless Sabrina was the emcee and narrator. This subseries contains ephemera related to the beauty contest event itself including Flawless Sabrina pageant business cards, event invitation, a Robert Kennedy letter declining the invitation, and an event program. Promotional material for the movie, budgets, press clippings, marketing packets, movie stills of the contestants, and a filming agreement with a list of the participants and their payments are also in this subseries. Of note are photographs from the 1968 Cannes Film Festival including images from events and a movie screening which were attended by Doroshow, Doroshow as Flawless Sabrina, and one of the contestants, Rachel Harlow. This subseries also contains promotional material and press clippings surrounding screenings of the movie in the 1990s and 2010s.
    This subseries is arranged chronologically.
    - The Nationals Corporation Business Card for Flawless Sabrina, circa 1959-1968 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Miss All-American Camp Beauty Pageant -- Invitation and Program, 1967-02-20 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Miss All-American Camp Beauty Pageant -- Invitation Regret Letter from Robert Kennedy, 1967-02-20 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Telegram from Jack Doroshow to His Mother re: Movie, 1967-10-14 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Contract for Documentary Movie, Letters, and List of Participants and their Payments, 1967-1968 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Press Clippings, 1967-1973 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Film Press Packet / Publicity Material, circa 1968 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Movie Poster, 1968; cuid39115 (Flat-file-folder 5, Box Electronic Records, E-records FA_MSS_594_ER_1)
    - Press Release, circa 1968 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Photographs -- Promotional Movie Stills, circa 1968 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Civil Court Judgement Between Jack Doroshow / National Academy and IBM Corporation, 1968-03-20 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Photographs by Jill Krimentz -- Flawless Sabrina and Photographers Parents, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Photographs by Pierre Manciet -- Flawless Sabrina, Rachel Harlow, Alan Delain, and Others at Cannes Film Festival, May 1968 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Photographs by Pierre Manciet -- Flawless Sabrina and Others at Dinner at Cannes Film Festival, May 1968 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Photographs by Pierre Manciet -- Flawless Sabrina and Rachel Harlow at Cannes Film Festival, May 1968 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Photographs -- Film Screening at the Cannes Film Festival with Ringo Starr, Jack Doroshow, Rachel Harlow, and Others, May 1968 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Photographs by Maurice Gaulmin -- Rachel Harlow, Jack Doroshow, and Others at Cannes Film Festival, May 1968 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Accounting Report for Film, Budget, 1968-1971 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Book Contract with Pyramid Publications, 1972-1975 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Letter re: Potential Television Show, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Notes on Concepts for Musical, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Si Litvinoff Recollections on The Queen, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - 1990s Release of Film -- Promotional Material and Still Photographs, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 22-23)
    - Financial Distribution History, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - 1990s Release of Film -- Notes and Memos, 1993-1994 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Press Clippings, 1993-1995 (Box 1, Folder 26-27)
    - Film Forum Advertising and Marketing for the Release, circa 1995 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Book -- Images of America: Gay and Lesbian Philadelphia with Entry for Jack Doroshow and The Queen, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Transnation Film Festival -- Movie Poster / Event Listings, 2016 (Box 51, Folder 1)
    - Promotional Material for Screening Event at Mother, undated (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Subseries I.B. The Apple Pie Show, 1983-1985
    This subseries contains material from Doroshow's unsuccessful attempt to produce The Apple Pie Show, a television talk show that would have been hosted by filmmaker John Waters and performer Divine during the 1980s. This subseries includes business cards, agreements with potential investors, press releases, shot lists, production schedules, budgets, and correspondence with John Waters and Divine, all related to the development of the show. Color sketches of caricatures of Divine in various costumes, set design images, logo mock-ups, and original painted story boards are also in this subseries. Proposal packets include letters of support, narratives describing the premise of the show, storyboards, budgets, and press releases which were distributed to potential investors and stakeholders. Also included in this subseries is Doroshow's handwritten preparatory script for his phone call with John Waters, as well as an audio recording of the conversation, along with a typed transcript.
    - Treatment for Show and Related Memo, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Robert Keenan Investment / Partnership Agreement, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - John Waters Phone Call -- Script, Audio Recording, Transcript of Call Conversation, 1983-12-06 (Box 3, Folder 11, Box Shared Fales 094, Audiocassette 594_005)
    - Divine Correspondence and Research, 1983-1984 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - John Waters Correspondence and Agreements, 1983-1984 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Agreements, Contracts, and Copyright Marks, 1983-1985 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Apple Pie Video and Apple Pie TV Business Cards and Letterhead, 1983-1985 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Show Proposal / Presentation Packets and Supporting Documents, 1983-1985 (Box 2, Folder 4-14, Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Phone Script to Market the Show, 1983-1985 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Show Shot List and Production Schedule, circa 1983-1985 (Box 2, Folder 16, Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Photographs of Set Design Mock-ups, circa 1983-1985 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Collage with Images of John Waters, Divine, and Cartoon Caricatures, circa 1983-1985 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Byron Guthrie Art Promotional Flier with "Something is Cooking on Your T.V. Set", circa 1983-1985 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Illustrations of Characters, Model Sheets, and Sketches, circa 1983-1985 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Color Graphics and Original Story Boards, circa 1983-1985 (Box 51, Folder 2)
    - Sketch of the Show Logo / Title Screen, circa 1983-1985 (Box 51, Folder 3)
    - Animation Quote Breakdown, circa 1983-1985 (Box 51, Folder 4)
    - Investor Agreements and Correspondence, 1983-1985 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Notes, circa 1983-1985 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Budget, Finances, circa 1983-1985 (Box 3, Folder 18, Box 4, Folder 1)
    - General Correspondence, 1983-1984, undated (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Beach St. Productions Agreement, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Joe Franklin Letter, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Jeff Haddow Letter, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Dick Roffman Show Correspondence and Press Release to Promote Show, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence -- Mothers Sound Stage, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Animation Company Estimate, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence re: TV Networks, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence re: Cinemax, 1984 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Ivan Kramarevsky Investor Agreements, Correspondence, 1984-1985 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Day Video Estimates, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Mock-ups of Promotional Material and Correspondence re: Potential Filming at the Limelight club, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Mock-up of Promotional Material, Agreements, and Correspondence re: Using Studio 54 for Filming, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 8, Box 4, Folder 4-5)
  - Subseries I.C. General Project Files, 1960s-2005, undated
    This subseries includes realized and unrealized Doroshow projects in movies, television, and theater, with him in the role of producer, writer, or actor, dating from the 1960s to the early 2000s. The subseries contains proposals and correspondence for Doroshow's partnership in the 1970s with writer Rona Jaffee including Baby Rainbow and All My Friends' Secrets. Documentation of acting projects include call sheets, scene lists, and residual reports for his bit part in The Anderson Tapes. Files in this subseries on propspective television shows Miss Cellaneous, Only In New York and an untitled video cabaret show include correspondence and presentation packets. Doroshow's production of the 1970s movie More, More, More files include agreements, budget, screenplay, promotional material, and soundtrack planning with songwriter Greg Diamond. This subseries also includes scrapbooks containing tracking notes for many of these projects, as well as actor headshots from the 1970s and 1980s which were retained by Doroshow in consideration for parts in various projects he was developing. Audio recordings from the project A Musical History of the Vietnam War are also in this subseries.
    This subseries is arranged chronologically, within groupings of files.
    - Actor and Model Headshots for Various Projects, circa 1960s-1980s (Box 4, Folder 6-8)
    - Rona Jaffee Projects -- Correspondence, 1967, undated (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Rona Jaffee Projects -- Baby Rainbow Correspondence, 1969 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Rona Jaffee Projects -- Certificate of Incorporation for Doroshow's Company, Dor, Inc., 1970 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Rona Jaffee Projects -- Contracts with Dor, Inc., 1970 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Rona Jaffee Projects -- Agreement re: Film Rights to Hair Correspondence, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Rona Jaffee Projects -- All My Friends' Secrets -- Drafts, Notes, Edits, 1970s (Box 4, Folder 14-15)
    - Personal Manager Agreement for Jack Doroshow, 1970 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - TV Project -- New York Cabaret Synopsis, 1970s-1980s (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Acting Project -- The Anderson Tapes Call Sheets, Scene Lists, Guild Residual Reports, 1970, 2008 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Multiple Projects -- Lists, Notes, and Letters, 1970-2001 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - TV Project -- A Day in the Life of... Synopsis, 1971 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Film Project -- I Ate Eros Proposal, 1971 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Film Project -- Slap Outline and Letter, 1971 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Film Project -- Sheila -- Agreement, Notes, Script Pages, circa 1971 (Box 5, Folder 8-11)
    - Notebook -- Multiple Project Status Reports, Contact Lists, and Meeting Notes -- (Slap, Baby Rainbow, Sheila, Rona Jaffee, and Other Projects, 1971-1978 (Box 45)
    - Film Project -- Mary Ann -- Synopsis and Script Pages, 1974 (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Film Project -- Lion's Share -- Agreement, Outline, Notes, Letters, 1974-1975 (Box 5, Folder 13, Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Apirations Productions, Inc. -- Blank Stock Certificates, Checks, Certificate of Incorporation, 1975 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Film Project -- Desdemona, Chinzano and Raw -- Partnership Offer, 1975 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Film Project -- More, More, More -- Agreements, Budget, Soundtrack Planning with Greg Diamond, Screenplay, Promotional Material, 1975-1977 (Box 6, Folder 4-13)
    - Film Project -- The Babysitter Script, July 1976 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Film Project -- Posessed Agreement, 1976 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Film Project -- Nickel Mountain Finance and Production Plan, 1977 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Film Project -- Comin' Up Letter and Presentation Packet, 1979 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Film Project -- Death Beat Letter, Script, Budget, 1980 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Len Aitken Productions -- Promotional Material, circa 1980 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Theater Project -- Strawhead Script, circa 1980-1983 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Theater Project -- Play Scripts by Mark Malone, 1981 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Film Project -- The Journey Treatment, Summary Presentation, 1982 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - TV Project -- Miss Cellaneous -- Presentation Packet, Phone Script for Soliciting, Budget, Correspondence, Location Information, 1983 (Box 7, Folder 10-15)
    - Film Project -- The Last Nazi Script, 1983-10-10 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - TV Project -- Variety Videos I, II, and III Proposal, circa 1983 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Film Project -- Liquid Sky Business Cards, Logo Mock-up, Correspondence, Weekly Gross Reports, 1983-1984 (Box 8, Folder 3, Box 51, Folder 5)
    - TV Project -- Video Cabaret Proposal, 1984 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Film Project -- Camp Pains Proposal, 1984 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Film Project -- How to Be a Television Talk Show Host Proposal, 1985 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Film Project -- Frontiers in Biological Psychiatry Proposal, 1985 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - TV Project -- Music Mansion Proposal, 1986 (Box 8)
    - Film Project -- Forecast Proposal, 1989 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - TV Project -- Probe Vision Proposal, 1992 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - Theater Project -- Feminine Wiles Script Draft, 2002 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Jack Script Dialogue, January 2005 (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - Psociopathetik Experiences -- Use of Jack's Apartment for Filming, 2005 (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - Film Project -- Chicken Pox Script with Flawless Sabrina Role, 2005 (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - Film Project -- Serpico Production Handbook, undated (Box 8, Folder 14)
    - Film Project -- Daddy Proposal Material, undated (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Film Project -- Wallstreet Mob Proposal Material, Mock-ups, undated (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Film Project -- The Hitch Hiker Script, undated (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Jim Mannix, Jr. -- Television Show Writing Samples, undated (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Film Project -- Proposal for Movie about Alice Cooper, undated (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Theater Project -- Unknown Show Character Descriptions, undated (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Film Project -- Broken Goddess with Holly Woodlawn Proposal, Photographs, undated (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Theater Project -- Doctor Noguchi Script, undated (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - TV Project -- Only in New York Proposal, undated (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - Theater Project -- Unknown Script, including Characters "Golightly" and "Solomon", undated (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - Theater Project -- Unknown Script, including Character "Jack", undated (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - Film Project -- Coffee and Commerce Outline, undated (Box 9, Folder 12)
    - Letterhead and Business Cards for Doroshow Working as a Producer, undated (Box 9, Folder 13)
    - A Musical History of the Vietnam War, undated (Box Shared Fales 094, Audiocassette 594_001 -- 594_004)
    - Photographs -- Unknown Stage Play, undated (Box 9, Folder 20)